<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd"
[
	<!ENTITY % wdb.entities SYSTEM "../docbook/wdb_entities.ent">
	%wdb.entities;
]
>

<chapter id="cha:stationload_system-design-specification">
	
	<title>StationLoad - System Design Specification</title>
	
	<sect1>
		<title>Introduction</title>
		
		<para>This document is the System Design Specification of the WDB weather station Loading program.</para>
		
		<sect2>
			<title>Purpose</title>
			
			<para>The system design specification provides a comprehensive overview of
			      the design of the software system. It is intended to make it easier for new
			      developers of WDB to become productive developing on the system.</para>
			
		</sect2>
		
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1>
		<title>System Overview</title>
		
		<sect2>
			<title>Work Domain</title>
			
			<figure id="fig:stationload_work-domain">
				<title>Work domain and work flow of the StationLoad system</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject role="html">
						<imagedata align="center"
							fileref="gfx/stationload_work-domain.png" format="PNG"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			
			<para><xref linkend="fig:stationload_work-domain"/> provides an overview of
				the work domain and the work flow of the WDB weather stations loading system.</para>
			
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2>
			<title>Technical Platform</title>
			
			<para>The stations loading software requires the following operating
				environment:</para>
			
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Hardware: Desktop PC</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Operating System: Linux</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>PostgreSQL version 8.1.x</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>libpqxx version 2.6.8</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Postgis version 1.3.x</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Boost 1.33.x</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Log4Cpp version 1.0</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>GEOS version 3.0.0</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			
		</sect2>
		
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1>
		<title>System Architecture</title>
		
		<para>The following section describes the architecture of the stationLoad utility.</para>
		
		<sect2>
			<title>Components</title>
			
                        <para>The stationLoad utility consists of three logical components. Each of these
                              components handles one of the key sequences of the task. The main stationLoad
                              program generally takes (as an in-arguments) the connection parameters to both 
                              the STINFOSYS and the WDB database.
                       
                              The STINFOSYS is the source for the weather stations records.
                              The STInfosysDatabseConnection will query all station records and forward
                              them to the WDBDatabaseConnection object.
                       
                             
                              Weather stations meta-data is then loaded in WDB database.
                              This is the job for WDBDatabaseConnection object.
                         </para>
			
			<sect3>
                                <title>Database object initialization</title>
				
                                <para>The main app initializes connections towards STINFOSYS and WDB databases.
                                      This is done by creating STInfosysDatabseConnection and WDBDatabaseConnection instances.</para>
				
			</sect3>
			
			<sect3>
                                <title>Getting the stations from STINFOSYS</title>
				
                                <para>STInfosysDatabseConnection extracts records and fills container.
                                      The getAllStations() method is used for this purpose.
                                      On the command line --after value can be specified.
                                      This will limit this result based on the last stations update date.
                                      If no --after value specified, all station records will be retreived from STINFOSYS.
                                      This suggested behavior for initial loading.
                                      The use of --after option is suggested when syncing tha data in WDB, once the intial loading has been performed.</para>
				
			</sect3>
			
			<sect3>
                                <title>Updating stations in WDB</title>
				
                                <para>The updateStations method of the WDBDatabaseConnection class takes the records obtained from STINFOSYS database. 
                                      The WDBDatabaseConnection goes through each record and calls addOrUpdatePlacePoint. The new record in WDB will be created,
                                      or the existing one will be updated. The intention is to 'copy' the stations history from STINFOSYS to WDB as close as possible.
                                </para>
				
			</sect3>
			
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2>
			<title>Dependencies</title>
			
			<sect3>
				<title>libPQXX</title>
				
				<para>The database API used in the StationLoad software is the libPQXX library for C++.</para>
				
			</sect3>
						
			<sect3>
				<title>Log4cpp</title>
				
				<para>Log4cpp is library of C++ classes for flexible logging to files,
				      syslog, IDSA and other destinations. It is modeled on the Log4j Java
				      library. Log4cpp is used to handle logging from the StationLoad system.
				      Log4cpp is encapsulated by the wdbLogHandler library.</para>
				
			</sect3>
			
			<sect3>
				<title>wdbException</title>
				
				<para>WdbException is the default exception class for the WDB system based
				      on std::exception. It is encapsulated in the wdbException library.</para>
				
			</sect3>
			
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2>
			<title>Program Interface</title>
			
			<para>stationLoad is a command-line tool. Its primary functionality 
                              is executed by writing the program name followed by the
			      station source parameters (or main configuration file), as follows:</para>
			
                        <para>stationLoad --conf /etc/stationload.cfg</para>
			
                        <para>In addition to the base functionality, the StationLoad system offers a number of additional options.</para>
			
			<itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
					<para>--help</para>
					<para>Produces the help message and then exits.</para>
				</listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                        <para>--version</para>
                                        <para>Produce version information and then exits.</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                        <para>--config FILENAME.CONF</para>
                                        <para>Main configuration file that defines command line options.
                                              Options given on the command line will override values in config file.</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                        <para>--cns-namespace ARG</para>
                                        <para>Specify wdb palcenamespaceid where metadata is to be stored with stationid
                                        (within STINFOSYS) as value for place name. The default placenamespace is 88000.</para>
                                        <para>Make sure that placenamespaceid is already created in the WDB!</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                        <para>--wmo-namespace ARG</para>
                                        <para>Specify wdb palcenamespaceid where metadata is to be stored with WMO number
                                        (within STINFOSYS) as value for place name. The default placenamespace is 88001.</para>
                                        <para>Make sure that placenamespaceid is already created in the WDB!</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                        <para>--logfile FILENAME.LOG</para>
                                        <para>Set output logfile. The default is to print to stdout</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                        <para>--loglevel LEVEL</para>
                                        <para>Sets the logging level, from 1 (most) to 5 (least)</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                        <para>--dry-run</para>
                                        <para>
                                              Dumps the list of SQL commands that would be sent to WDB.
                                              No execution takes place. Useful for debugging.
                                        </para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                        <para>--after</para>
                                        <para>Lower bound on the update date for stations. Accepts several date formats (see man date), like:
                                              "Thu Aug 30 09:38:43 CEST 2012", "2012-08-21", "1997-07-16T19:20+01:00", "20012/08/21" etc.
                                              Use (double/single) quotes to delimit date value.
                                        </para>
                                        <para>If the value is missing stationLoad will take all entries from STINFOSYS - god for inital wdb loading.</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                        <para>-d DBNAME</para>
                                        <para>--database=DBNAME</para>
                                        <para>Specify the database name to connect to (e.g., wdb).</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                        <para>-h DBHOST</para>
                                        <para>--host=DBHOST</para>
                                        <para>Specify the database host to connect to (e.g., somehost.met.no).</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                        <para>-u DBUSER</para>
                                        <para>--user=DBUSER</para>
                                        <para>Specify the WDB user to connect as. The database user must have
                                              access to the wdb_grib role (this is will usually be the case if the
                                              stationLoad process is being run by the creator of the database).
                                        </para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                        <para>-p DBPORT</para>
                                        <para>--port=DBPORT</para>
                                        <para>Specify the database port to connect to (e.g., 5432).</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                        <para>--stdatabase=STINFOSYS_DBNAME</para>
                                        <para>Specify the STINFOSYS database name to connect to (e.g., stinfosys).</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                        <para>--sthost=STINFOSYS_DBHOST</para>
                                        <para>Specify the STINFOSYS host to connect to (e.g., somehost.met.no).</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                        <para>--stuser=STINFOSYS_DBUSER</para>
                                        <para>Specify the STINFOSYS user to connect as.</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                        <para>--stport=STINFOSYS_PORT</para>
                                        <para>Specify the STINFOSYS port to connect to (e.g., 5432).</para>
                                </listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			
		</sect2>
		
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1>
		<title>Core Design</title>
		
		<para>The following section describes the core design of the StationLoad system.</para>
		
		<sect2>
			<title>Database Design</title>
			
                        <para>For the up-to-date and complete description look into the WDB documentation.</para>
                        <para>The keywords to be searchd are: placename, placenamespaceid, wci.addOrUpdatePlacePoint etc.</para>
			
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2>
			<title>Classes and Functionality</title>
			
			<para><xref linkend="fig:stationload_class-diagram"/> is the class diagram of
				the StationLoad system. It describes the classes in the system, as well as the
				interrelationship of the classes with the various function sets.</para>
			
			<figure id="fig:stationload_class-diagram">
				<title>Class diagram of the StationLoad system</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject role="html">
						<imagedata align="center"
							fileref="gfx/stationload_class-diagram.png"
							format="PNG"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			
			<para>This is not intended to be an exhaustive description of the classes and
                                functions in the program; for that, review the code itself.</para>
			
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2>
			<title>Main Program Routine</title>
			
			<para>The functionality of the main program is as follows:</para>
			
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Parse the options from the command line</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Connect to the STINFOSYS database</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
                                        <para>Read the STI stations records (all if no --after option given or just those whose update time is >= after)</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
                                        <para>Forward the list of obtained records to WDBDatabaseConnection object</para>
				</listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                        <para>Call WDBDatabaseConnection.updateStations to add/update records in the WDB database</para>
                                </listitem>

				<listitem>
                                        <para>Close database connections</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Terminate the program</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2>
			<title>STIStationRecord</title>
			
                        <para>The STIStationRecord class encapsulates data from a single STINFOSYS record (as defined in station table).</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2>
                        <title>STInfosysDatabaseConnection</title>
			
                        <para>The STInfosysDatabase class inherits pqxx::conection.
                              Encapsulates the STINFOSYS databse. Useful function:</para>
			
			<sect3>
                                <title>getAllStations</title>
				
                                <para>Extracts stations from the station table. Takes out all stations or the ones filtered by --after value.</para>
				
			</sect3>
			
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2>
                        <title>WDBDatabaseConnection</title>
			
                        <para>The WDBDatabaseConnection class inherits pqxx::conection.
                                Contains function calls for all the WDB database access.</para>
			
			<para>To maximize performance during loading, most SQL statements and cursors
				are prepared and declared only once. The database must be indexed such that
				all searches made occur using indexed search.</para>
			
                        <para>updateStations is the most important function. Here we will loop through all
                              the records from STINFOSYS and insert new or update exisitng WDB records.
                              The idea is to keep stations history in sync between WDB and STINFOSYS databases.</para>
			
                        <para>IMPORTANT-. WDB is using two placenamespaceids: one to insert stations with the stationid (originating from STINFOSYS) as key,
                              and the other where WMO number is used as key.
                              By default the first uses 88000 and the other uses 88001 as placenamespaceid.
                        </para>

		</sect2>
		
		<sect2>
			<title>Error Handling</title>
			
			<para>Errors in the StationLoad system are resolved through exception handling
			      based on the WdbException base class. All errors are logged using the
			      Log4cpp library for writing log files (encapsulated in wdbLog).</para>
			
		</sect2>
		
	</sect1>
	
</chapter>
